Guide to the Arthur Kopit Papers MSS.141
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series I: Projects
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 1, 1973-1976; 31142040620075 (Box 65)
    The Frog
    Unknown work fragments
    Promontory Point Revisited
    Hamburger, French Fries and a Coke
    Masters of the Wind
    Lewis and Clark--Lost and Found
    Asylum
    Undated screenplay of "The Frogs." Outline of children's work "The Woblns" (see also box 9) which seems to have morphed into "Masters of the Wind." Proposals, descriptions and outlines for that work, apparently a collaborative travelling show based on ecological issues. "Hamburger...." and "Lewis and Clark" may have been other contributions or evolutions of this concept by Kopit as many of the records are found together and all works were planned around the Bicentennial celebrations of 1976. Handwritten and typewritten script drafts of "Asylum", "Endplay". Pamphlets, ephemera, and other materials on human rights, ecology, arts organizations and miscellaneous materials.
    Note: One folder of slides and photographs of art by "Peter Nicholson". 1 folder of oversized drawing from "Lewis and Clark" moved to Flat Box 11.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 2, 1991-1993; 31142040620091 (Box 66)
    The Virginian, Envy, Traffik, Haley's Cam.
    Newspapers, magazines, index cards and handwritten notes, drafts, scripts (not written by Kopit) of "Another World" soap opera.
    Owen Wister, The Virginian (Grosset and Dunlap: New York, 1904)
    Owen Wister, The Virginian (Penguin Books: New York, 1988)
    "for Traffik: 'Inside edition' Mexican Drug Trade" VHS
    "Wings...Envy"
    "envy 2/3/93"
    "Envy-1/19/93"
    "Envy 2nd conversation 1/21/93"
    "Envy--conversation with Barbara Lieberman 3/11/93"
    "Becky: Virginian" 1 micro cassette
    Note: One folder of folded large sheets at end of box to be separated out.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 3 (Scripts Box 1), 31142040620083 (Box 67)
    "Good Help is Hard to Find" ca. 1980
    "Secrets of the Rich"
    Index cards and notes for "Secrets..."
    "The Questioning of Nick" ca. 1957
    "Fresh Game" multiple copies of film treatment, undated
    "Fresh Game" first typescript parts of novel "fortunately! never finished" undated
    "Oh Dad, Poor Dad...." Jan 9. 1962
    "Oh Dad, Poor Dad..." 1960. "This is the original script without the extensive revisions which went into the Harvard production of January 7, 1960."
    "oh Dad, Poor Dad..." galleys
    "Chamber Music" undated draft, ca. 1971
    "Chamber Music" French Translation, 1972
    "King of the Heap" Undated original typescript with corrections.
    "Snatch" undated handwritten script.
    Box also contains various index cards and notes, some likely from Lesley Garis.
    Notebook of "Lewis and Clark" ideas
    "Animal Hospital" 1986
    "Mhil'daiim" 3/16/1964 and other dates, extensive rough typescript and finished copies
    "What's Happened to the Thorne's House" ca. 1972 (in envelope labeled "Landgrove Play") typescript, revisions, copies, with handwritten production notes.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 4 (Scripts Box 2), 31142040619747 (Box 68)
    "Louisiana Territory or Lewis and Clark...." descriptive booklet
    "End of the World...." undated
    "Discovery of America" undated, lacking Act I scene 1.
    "On the Runway of Life You Never Know What's Coming Off Next" ca. 1958
    "Indians" Scandinavian translation, undated
    series of working drafts and revisions of "Good Help is Hard to Find" ca. 1981
    "Business Day" proposal and notes for radio play, undated
    "Staying Afloat", teleplay written with Davis Weinstock, 1979, includes handwritten notes and revisions.
    "The Day the Whores Came Out to Play Tennis" ca. 1964, typescripts with hand revisions and edits, extensive handwritten drafts
    "An Incident in the Park" rough typescript with revisions, ca. 1968
    "Endplay" undated, typescripts
    "Asylum" ca. 1963, rough typescripts with hand revisions.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 5 (Scripts Box 3), 31142040619754 (Box 69)
    "!" undated screenplay based on other authors' play "Who Wants to Kill Jessie?"
    "Treasure Island" 2/28/94 (first draft)and 12/17/94 (2nd draft)
    "Discovery of America" undated
    "Roswell" undated
    "Between the Wars" 12/15/92
    "Sweet Smell of Success" plot outlines, ca. 8/23/1994
    "Wings" teleplay 11/9/93
    "Oh Dad, Poor Dad..." undated copies, one mimeographed copy with hand edits and alterations; scrapbook and news clippings from the early 1960s mostly documenting "Oh Dad, Poor Dad..." and galleys from some early edition.
    "Phantom" revisions and typescript.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 6 (Scripts Box 7), 31142040619796 (Box 70)
    "Masquerade", notebooks audio tapes (see below), handwritten notes and magazine for original movie idea, ca. 1996
    "Ideas for 'Harvey' as an updated film", "Ideas for adaptation of 'Mr. Blandings...'" ca. 1999
    "Sophia Calle" Paul Auster novel, articles, some notes for possible work, ca. 1999
    "Sweet Smell of Success" initial contract with Livent, copyright documents and documents relating to project in respect to Livent's bankruptcy, 1995-1999
    "The Nina Play", notes, notebooks, tapes and computer media (see below) on work.
    "Comfortable Shoes" Clint Holmes musical; video tape, CD, notebook and notes on possible work, 2000
    Ephemera including replica of doubloon, permit for public meeting for "Lewis and Clark"
    "Hollywood Play" also noted as "City of Faith Part III" ("Discovery of America" was sometimes subtitled "City of Faith Part I"), Typescript with hand edits
    "Nine" script fragment
    "Hands of a Stranger", various drafts, 1986-1987
    "Till Death Us Do Part" final version without Kopit's credit, 1991
    "Lewis and Clark..." notebook of handwritten ideas, undated
    "A Treatment for the Adaptation of 'Who Wants to Kill Jessie?' (Later titled "!"), undated
    Notebook of ideas for "Hamburger, French Fires, and a Coke", "The Wobbls", et al., undated
    "Landgrove Play" (later retitled...Thorne's House" typescript draft and hand notes, undated
    "Promontory Point Revisited" teleplay script, undated
    "Le Placard", French translation of "Oh Dad, Poor Dad...", undated, and photo of Istanbul production
    Paul Auster, Leviathan (Penguin Books: New York, 1993)
    "Clint Holmes 4/2000" VHS
    "Seduction"
    "(Seduction) this tape is at 278" 1 micro cassette
    "Masquerade" 1 micro cassette in env.
    "Tape recorder and obsession tape" two micro cassettes and recorder in padded env.
    "Play about woman who can't remember..." (Nina Play) 2 micro cassettes in env.
    Other Recordings
    "Selections from 'Comfortable Shoes' CD, 1998
    "Louisville play NINA 4/20/95" 1 5" floppy disk
    Note: Oversized materials moved to Flat Box 11: one folder of "Notes on 'Men Are From Mars...'; roll of large pencil sketches, apparently studies for "Lewis and Clark"; Oversized sketchbook pages of "Blindsight"; Photocopies of handwritten drafts of "Discovery of America"; photocopied book "The Two Hundred Days of 8 1/2" by Deena Boyer...."; oversized notebook, apparently of "Mhil'Daiim"
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 7 (Scripts Box 8), 31142040619770 (Box 71)
    "Discovery of America" copious typescript versions, revisions, and fragments, original notes, notes on "Masters of the Wind" possibly related
    Notes on "Hollywood" City of Faith Part III, ca. 1974
    "An Incident in the Park", typescript ca. 1964
    "Wings", undated
    "Hands of a Stranger" various copies, drafts, notes, correspondence and other documents relating to production, ca. 1986-1987.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 8 (Scripts Box 9), 31142040619788 (Box 72)
    "Blue Angel: index cards,, notes; 1st and 3rd drafts, 1993
    "'Fat City' or 'The Winner' original screenplay typescript by Kopit and Coco Brown, ca. 1968
    "The Questioning of Nick", multiple undated copies
    "Asylum" unedited typescript
    "Phantom" reject pages, playbill, research
    "The Conquest of Everest" undated multiple copies, original typescript with hand edits
    "Untitled Play", undated typescript
    "Fresh Game" screenplay outline
    "The Day the Whores Came Out to Play Tennis" undated typescript
    "Snatch" photocopy of typescript, ca. 1968
    "Discovery of America" fragment
    "Scarlet Pimpernel" act one typescript
    "Wings" teleplay draft, 1991
    "Indians", correspondence, reviews and other materials focusing on production by Terry Hands ca. 1992 in Germany; large amount of fax correspondence concerning German production, an adaptation renamed "Buffalo Bill" and a subsequent contest of rights and copyright, reviews
    "Between the Wars" various drafts, 1992
    "Roswell" 1992, plus research
    "The Poet" 2nd draft of screenplay, 1991-1992
    Note: Oversized materials moved to Flat Box 12: handwritten and typescript drafts, character sketches, outlines, and exploration of names, all for unknown work dated 1975.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 9 (Scripts Box 12), 31142040619762 (Box 73)
    "The Poet", 1st and 2nd drafts of screenplay, 1990-1991
    "The Frog" screenplay numerous copies including original handwritten draft and original typescript with hand edits undated
    "Fresh Game" 2 different versions of film outline, undated
    fragment of unknown work
    "Starstruck", materials for unproduced science fiction tv series including binders and notebooks, index cards, script, audiotape, handwritten and typescript notes, character outlines, time lines, etc., ca.1978
    Handwritten and typescript drafts of undated work entitled "Sensuous Woman"
    "End of the World", two copies of script
    "Starstruck 8/13/78" 1 micro cassette
    Note: 1 folder of legal size material on "Starstruck" moved to Flat Box 12.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 10 (Scripts Box 12), 31142040619812 (Box 74)
    "The Day the Whores..." "first draft orig. hand-written", undated, and multiple typescripts ca. 1964
    "On the Runway of Life..." undated handwritten drafts and finished typescripts
    "Mhil'Daiim" multiple copies, undated
    "Untitled Play" undated
    "Edgar's Exploits" undated script for play, no other records for work found
    "Sing to Me Through Open Windows" handwritten and typescript draft, ca. 1961
    "Promontory Point Revisited" along with other authors' works included in N.Y. Television Theater, 1969
    "Bone-the-Fish" 1st draft, 1988
    "Deception" undated
    "Hands of a Stranger" 1st draft, 1986
    "Legacy of a Mother's Murder" 3rd draft 1990
    Drafts and materials of unknown work, ca. 1980s or early 1990s
    "partial original typescript of unknown work, 1965?
    Note: One folder of draft of "Snatch" legal-sized pages moved to Flat Box 12
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 11, ca. 1965-1993; 31142040619804 (Box 75)
    Materials relating to development of musical called "Eureka"; letter to Andrew Lloyd Weber regarding Phantom; book and videotapes from "Between the Wars"; writings by Roger Garis including the play, "Some Don't", ca. 1965, and the novella "The Stepping Stone"; Materials on "Dreamhouse" including script fragments, notes and revisions, research including articles and newspapers; "Ropongo" materials; tapes and some materials relating to "Deception", and drafts and script of play by Kopit called "Padding".
    Ernest Hemingway, The Fifth Column and Four Stories of the Spanish Civil War (Charles Scribner's Sons: New York, 1972)
    Ground Zero, Nuclear War: What's in it for You? (Pocket Books: New York, 1982)
    David Talbot Rice, Islamic Art (Thames and Hudson: New York, 1986)
    "The Spanish Civil War" 3 tapes
    "The War Reporters"
    "The Good Fight"
    "Songs by Maurice Jarre"
    Tape related to Eureka wrapped inside letter in envelope
    "Alex's Comments on Dreamhouse"
    "Dreamhouse phone call to Michael Mannheim"
    "{Dreamhouse July '93" 1 micro tape
    "Ropongo Tapes" 5 micro tapes in envelope
    "Becky Interviews Police about smuggling"
    "Marlo Thomas Deception" 1 micro tape
    Note: Oversized material includes folder of "Eureka" Materials, large sketchbook pages for "Dreamhouse", moved to Flat Box 12
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 12, 31142040619820 (Box 76)
    files on various works, mostly relating to foreign productions including translations, royalties, correspondence, programs, reviews and contracts. Works include "Chamber Music", "Discovery of America", "End of the World", "Indians" (Including the "Original Hand Written Version!"), "Oh Dad, Poor Dad...", "Nine" (including snapshots of French(?) company), "Road to Nirvana", and "Phantom". A second set of records then begins composed mainly of finished copies of scripts including "Edgar's Exploits", "The Conquest of Everest", "Untitled Play", "The Questioning of Nick", and "The Day the Whores....".
    Note: One oversized folder of material on "Chamber Music", one folder of "Oh Dad, Poor Dad..." (original film contract); one of "Nine", unidentified handwritten script from 1976, all moved to Flat Box 12.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 13, 31142040619838 (Box 77)
    Continues material from previous box; copies of scripts including "On the Runway of Life...", "Sing to me...:, "The Day the Whores...", and "Indians"; also contains sketchbook with notes on numerous works, an outline or short story entitled "Bunny Lake is Missing", handwritten notes and copies of materials on psychiatric and neurological testing; three videotapes and other materials on "Mind Control", and materials from a letter box labeled "Rock/Nina Play" including audio tapes, transcripts and research and a set of files marked "Nina/Rock Play Deconstruction and Mrs. Gaskell".
    "The X Files"
    "Dateline: MPD"
    "Conversation at Sotheby's"
    "Micro cassette from L400" 1 tape in envelope
    "Saturday August 5th Nina notes"1 tape in envelope
    "5/25/95 transcribe both sides" 1 tape in envelope
    1 unlabelled micro tape Audio Cassettes
    "Nina Strauss interview at her house June 5, 1995" 1 tape in envelope
    "6/8/95 Nina Strauss lunch" 2 tapes in 2 envelopes
    "Nina Strauss interviewed...5/25/95" 1 tape in envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 14, 31142040620109 (Box 78)
    Manuscript copy of book on Marlene Dietrich with annotations, most likely "Blue Angel" by Donald Spoto; a folder concerning a "10 minute play"; a script of "In a Child's Name", materials on "Between the Wars", assorted business files and ledgers, and notes and index cards of "The Poet". Following "The Poet" folder is a set of older records from the 1960s consisting of correspondence, contracts, files on "Lewis and Clark", materials from a teaching stint at Wesleyan, and a mixed folder of various older script fragments and notes. At the end of a box are materials related to an unproduced collaboration with Danny Elfman on a work of his creation called "Jimmy Callicutt".
    Audio Recordings
    45 rpm phonograph "Ninety-Nine and a Half" by Wilson Pickett.
    "Jimmy Callicutt demos"
    "Work of Jimmy Callicutt"
    Note: One folder of oversized material including correspondence and contracts with ICM and a French translation of "The Day the Whores..." moved to Flat Box 13.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 14, 31142040620117 (Box 79)
    Materials on "Scientific Process", a draft of "Phantom", a folder on "Wings", notes and materials removed from a tabbed binder on "Starstruck"; a group of materials including tapes and photographs on "In a Child's Name", magazines and sketchbook on unknown projects. An older series of records begins here including scripts and drafts of student works "Houdini", "To Dwell in a Place of Strangers", "Aubade", records of "Oh Dad...". Additional material,s from that time period here include 2 scrapbooks, magazines, reviews and ephemera.
    "Ken Taylor 13 Feb 1985"
    "Home Movies New Jersey News"
    "lecture"
    "Teresa Taylor Homicide"
    Note: One folder of oversized material, magazine, poster and photo from different years moved to Flat Box 13.
  - Miscellaneous Works 15, 31142050718678 (Box 80)
    A box composed completely of undifferentiated materials, as if swept from an office floor. Materials include copious amounts of newspaper, magazines, handwritten notes, index cards, etc. Very few folders, envelopes or other sorting and labeling devices are present.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 16, 31142050718686 (Box 81)
    The same as previous, seems to contain a large amount of oversized sketchy pad sheets. Most material seems handwritten.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 17, 31142050718694 (Box 82)
    The same as previous. A preponderance of spiral notebooks.
  - Miscellaneous Works Box 18, 31142050718710 (Box 83)
    The same as previous. Quantity of oversized sketchbook pages left in box.
    Note: 3 very large sketchbooks from "End of the World" moved to Flat Box 13
  - MK Ultra, 1950-1999; cuid22068 (Box 133, Box Shared Fales 013)
  - Note cards: Ideas, Characters, City of Faith, The Invisible Dick, The Tour, Gagarins, Houdini, cuid22069 (Box 135)
- Series II: Magazines, Newspapers and Other Media
  This series is divided by type of media into publications, video tapes, computer media and assorted media. Many books were found in the collection. Those that were obviously used for research, and were found with other materials for their respective projects, were left in place. Those that were found in discrete groups were separated from the collection. A list of those books can be found at back. Some of the books seem to have been used as research, some seem to be just discards from Kopit's personal library; many of the books are multiple copies of Kopit's published works. All but one copy of each edition have been removed from the collection. Other publications include magazines, playbills, programs and newspapers. Some have articles by or on Kopit,m some are periodicals acquired for research while others are in the collection for no apparent reason.
  The videotapes, a more extensive collection, include research on works (including prior versions of films and stories); home movies; feature tapes of performances of Kopit plays around the world; video copies of the daily reels of the filming of Roswell as well as preliminary versions of the entire film; nineteen U-matic tapes of unknown content though some seem to be home movies and recordings of tv shows.
  Computer media consist of a variety of materials. Most of the media are 5 inch floppy disks with numerous applications and programs; Kopit has often included printouts and notes for the contents and documentation of the computer system. Boxes 65 and 67 consist of numerous backups of drafts and scripts of works; among the disks are labels that refer to previously unmentioned works and projects including "The Poet", found on numerous disks and dated 1991; possible work done on an unproduced musical version of Tom Swift; "Tricks of the Trade", a project noted as being a "Bob Brown/Coco idea"; an unnamed project with Audrey Cooper; "The Byte of Love", "Hasten the Bullet", and "Arcata". Box 66 contains similar material as well as a significant collection of writings and materials by Kopit's wife, Leslie Garis (LG), and computer records by Kopit's children Alex, Ben and Katherine (Kat). The materials will be separated into their own box and placed at the end of the collection in their own series. Scattered throughout are disks of applications, operating systems, and utilities.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Magazines and Newspapers Box 1, 31142050718702 (Box 84)
    Magazines (particularly issues of "PC Magazine" to which Kopit had a subscription) and Playbills; multiple copies of the PMLA, Playboy,
  - Magazines and Newspapers Box 2, 1976-1995; 31142050718728 (Box 85)
    Whole papers and newspaper sections, most apparently from ca. 1976; science magazines from the early to mid 1990s.
  - Videotapes Box 1, ca.1991-1994; 31142050718736 (Box 86)
    All tapes are VHS unless otherwise noted
    "The Phantom of the Opera" Silent film
    "Interview"
    "'In a Child's Name' Part I"
    "In a Child's Name Part II + Interview with Taylor"
    "Wings 8/8/93 Reel 1 of 2"
    "Wings 8/8/93 Reel 2 of 2" professional dub
    "'Phantom of the Opera' Part 2 of 2 11/9/90" professional dub
    "Phantom of the Opera Temp Dub/Work Picture 11/30"
    "Roswell"
    "Phantom"
    "Alien 'autopsy' + Roswell stuff (not my film)"
    "Wings" Betamax
    "'Roswell' 1 of 1...6/21/94" Professional dub
    "Area 51"
    "'Phantom of the Opera' Part II...1/8/90" professional dub
    "The Cell Cycle: Featuring DNA replication and Mitosis; Ben Kopit"
    "The Cell Cycle, Mitosis, and Cell Division" Professional dub
    "Tape 2, Nov. 14, 1992"
    "Tape 1, Nov. 14, 1992""Jesse Marcel and others"
    "National Geographic...The Incredible Human Machine"
    "Part One-End of the World-Soviet Version"
    "Part Two-End of the World-Soviet Version"
    "'Nine' Aust. Cast via John Wiedrick"
    "Xmas '84"
    "Alley Theater Road to Nirvana"
    'Phantom of the Opera' Herbert Lom version"
    "Chicago Phantom TV Candlelight [Dinner Theater]"
    "East of Eden (1955) 1776 (1972) The Phantom of the Opera (1962)"
    "'In a Child's Name' Part II"
    "Ben's Science Film"
    "Ben's Tape--Mitosis, etc."
    "'Phantom of the Opera' Part 1 of 2 11/9/90"
    "New Year's Greetings to my mother and Jack"
    "Phantom of the Opera 10/27/89 Rough cut Erik Productions"
    "Phantom of the Opera Claude Rains"
    "'Roswell' half hour documentary after the film"
  - Videotapes Box 2, ca. 1993; 31142050718744 (Box 87)
    "Theater Arts" Magazine, April, 1961
    "Alien Life at Roswell"
    "protein Synthesis"
    "A Brief History of Time"
    "Ben Kopit, NCCS project, Feb 3, 1995"
    "Ben's DNA video, done with Eric"
    "Roswell Dailies"
    "Reels 119-125 Shot 12-15-93"
    "Reels 57-58 Dailies Shot 11/23/93"
    "Reels 107-110 Dailies Shot 12/9/93"
    "Reels 79, 89-94 Dailies Shot 12/1, [12]/3/93"
    "Reel 111 Dailies Shot 12/10/93"
    "Reels 13-18 Dailies Shot 11/9/93"
    "Reels 36-40 Dailies Shot 11/16/93"
    "Reels 95-99 Dailies Shot 12/6/93"
    "Reels 59MOS, 60 Dailies Shot 11/24/93"
    "Reels 7-10 Dailies Shot 11/8/93"
    "Reels 21-25 Dailies Shot 11/10/93"
    "Reels 2,4,11,12 Dailies Shot 11/8/93"
    "Reels 26-29 Dailies Shot 11/11/93; Reels 30-32 Dailies Shot 11/12/93"
    "Reels 19-20 Dailies Shot 11/9/93"
    "Reels 1,3,5,6 Make-Up Test Dailies Shot 11/5/93"
    "Reels 68-71 Dailies Shot 11/30/93"
    "Reels 80-88 Dailies Shot 12/02/93"
    "Reels 41-45 Dailies Shot 11/17/93"
    "Reels 72-78 Dailies Shot 12/01/93"
    "Reels 104-106 Dailies Shot 12/8/93"
    "Reels 46-50 Dailies Shot 11/12,17,18/93"
    "Reels 51-54 Dailies Shot 11/19/93"
    "Reels 112-116 Dailies Shot 12/13/93"
  - Video Tapes Box 3, 31142050718751 (Box 88)
    The following nineteen cassettes are all Sony KCS20 U-Matic cassettes. They are numbered twice on the spine, 1-19 and K122-K140 with additional abbreviated labels. There are extensive content notes with time signatures on the inside covers. None of the labels, interior or exterior, bear any reference to known projects or works by Kopit except some possible recordings of Lewis and Clark.
    "1 Huck, Pinball"
    "2 Barbershop, Jack-Stalk, Letters, Pieta, Fights"
    "3 Lulu+Clark, American Family, Box+Puppets"
    "4 Reel of Ahab, Yank"
    "5 Fights, subjective fights, samuri, gauze"
    "6 Gauze"
    "7 End piece"
    "8 Lois+Clark, Superman...Tempest, Pinball"
    9 [unlabeled]
    10 [unlabeled]
    11[unlabeled]
    12 [unlabeled]
    "13 Reception"
    "14 #1 Gauze in Circle"
    "15 Ahab + the cars"
    "16 Circle Game and Raoul Inter."
    "17 Morning Wkout"
    18 [unlabeled]
    19 [unlabeled]
  - Video Tapes Box 4, 31142050718769 (Box 89)